Chapter 51.
The Spirit Spout.
Days, weeks passed, and under easy sail the ivory peekquad had slowly swept
across four several cruising grounds.
That off the Azors, off the Cape Deveres, on the plate, so-called being
off the mouth of the Rio de la Plata, and the carol ground, an unstaked watery
locality southerntherly from St. Helena.
It was while gliding through these ladder waters that one serene and
moonlight night, when all the waves rolled by like scrolls of silver, and by
their soft, suffusing seething, made what seemed a silvery silence, not a
solitude. On such a silent night, a silvery jet was seen far in advance of
the white bubbles at the bow. Lit up by the moon, it looked celestial, seemed
some plumed and glittering god uprising from the sea. Fedala first described
this jet, for of these moonlight nights, it was his want to mount to the main
mast head and stand a lookout there with the same precision as if it had been
day. And yet, though herds of whales were seen by night, not one whaleman in
a hundred would venture a lowering for them. You may think with what emotions
then the seamen beheld this old oriental perched aloft at such unusual hours, his
turban and the moon companions in one sky. But when, after spending his
uniform interval there for several successive nights, without uttering a
single sound, when, after all this silence, his unearly voice was heard
announcing that silvery moonlit jet, every reclining mariner started to his
feet, as if some winged spirit had lighted in the rigging, and hailed the mortal crew.
There she blows.
Had the trump of judgment blown, they could not have quivered more, yet still
they felt no terror, rather pleasure.
For though it was a most unwanted hour, yet so impressive was the cry, and so
deliriously exciting that almost every soul on board instinctively desired a lowering.
Walking the deck with quick side lunging strides, Ahab commanded the tag gallant
sails and royals to be set, and every stunil spread. The best man in the ship
must take the helm. Then, with every mast head manned, the piled up craft
rolled down before the wind. The strange upheaving lifting tendency of the
taffrail breeze filling the hollows of so many sails made the buoyant hovering
deck to feel like air beneath the feet, while still she rushed along as if two
antagonistic influences were struggling in her, one to mount direct to heaven,
the other to drive yawingly to some horizontal goal. And had you watched
Ahab's face that night, you would have thought that in him also two different
things were waring. While his one live leg made lively echoes along the deck,
every stroke of his dead limb sounded like a coffin tap. On life and death
this old man walked. But though the ship so swiftly sped, and though from every
eye like arrows the eager glances shot, yet the silvery jet was no more seen
that night. Every sailor swore he saw it once, but not a second time.
This midnight spout had almost grown a forgotten thing, when some days after,
lo, at the same silent hour, it was again announced, again it was described
by all, but upon making sail to overtake it, once more it disappeared, as if it
had never been. And so it served us night after night, till no one heated it
but to wonder at it, mysteriously jetted into the clear moonlight or starlight as
the case may be, disappearing again for one whole day or two days or three, and
somehow seeming at every distinct repetition to be advancing still further
and further in our van. this solitary jet seemed forever alluring us on.
nor with the immemorial superstition of their race, and in accordance with the
preternaturalness, as it seemed, which in many things invested the Peekquad,
were there wanting some of the seammen who swore that whenever and wherever
described, at however remote times, or in however far apart latitudes and
longitudes, that unnearable spout, was cast by one self-same whale, and that whale, Moby Dick,
For a time there reigned, too, a sense of peculiar dread at this flitting
apparition, as if it were treacherously beckoning us on and on, in order that
the monster might turn round upon us, and rend us at last in the remotest and
most savage seas. These temporary apprehensions, so vague but so awful,
derived a wondrous potency from the contrasting serenity of the weather, in
which beneath all its blue blandness, some thought there lurked a devilish
charm, as for days and days we voyaged along through seas so wearily,
lonesomely mild, that all space, in repugnance to our vengeful errand,
seemed vacating itself of life before our ernlike prow.
But at last, when turning to the eastward, the Cape winds began howling
around us, and we rose and fell upon the long troubled seas that are there. When
the ivory tusked peekquad sharply bowed to the blast, and gored the dark waves
in her madness, till, like showers of silver chips, the foam flakes flew over
her bull works. Then all this desolate vacuity of life went away, but gave
place to sights more dismal than before.
Close to our boughs, strange forms in the water darted hither and thither
before us. While thick in our rear view flew the inscrable sea ravens, and every
morning perched on our stays, rows of these birds were seen, and in spite of
our hootings, for a long time obstinately clung to the hemp, as though
they deemed our ship some drifting, uninhabited craft, a thing appointed to
desolation, and therefore fit roosting place for their homeless selves. and
heaved and heaved, still unrestingly heaved the Black Sea, as if its vast
tides were a conscience, and the great mundane soul were in anguish and remorse
for the long sin and suffering it had bred.
Cape of good hope, do they call you?
Rather, Cape Tormanoto, as called of Yore, for long allured by the perfidious
silences that before had attended us, we found ourselves launched into this
tormented sea, where guilty beings transformed into those fowls in these
fish, seem condemned to swim on everlastingly, without any haven in
store, or beat that black air without any horizon. but calm, snow white, and
unvarying, still directing its fountain of feathers to the sky, still beckoning
us on from before. The solitary jet would at times be described.
During all this blackness of the elements, Ahab, though assuming for the
time the almost continual command of the drenched and dangerous deck, manifested
the glooiest reserve, and more seldom than ever, addressed his mates. In
tempestuous times like these, after everything above in a loft has been
secured, nothing more can be done but passively to await the issue of the
gale. Then captain and crew become practical fatalists. So with his ivory
leg inserted into its accustomed hole, and with one hand firmly grasping a
shroud, Ahab for hours and hours would stand gazing dead to windward, while an
occasional squall of sleet or snow, would all but congeal his very eyelashes
together. Meanwhile, the crew, driven from the forward part of the ship by the
perilous seas that burstingly broke over its boughs, stood in a line along the
bull works in the waist, and the better to guard against the leaping waves. Each
man had slipped himself into a sort of bolan, secured to the rail, in which he
swung as in a loosened belt. Few or no words were spoken, and the silent ship,
as if manned by painted sailors in wax, day after day, tore on through all the
swift madness and gladness of the demonic waves. By night, the same
muteness of humanity before the shrieks of the ocean prevailed. Still in silence
the men swung from the bolands. Still wordless Ahab stood up to the blast.
Even when wearied nature seemed demanding repose, he would not seek that
repose in his hammock. Never could Starbucks forget the old man's aspect,
when one night, going down into the cabin to mark how the barometer stood,
he saw him with closed eyes sitting straight in his floorcrewed chair, the
rain and half-melted sleet of the storm from which he had some time before
emerged, still slowly dripping from the unreved hat and coat. On the table
beside him lay unrolled one of those charts of tides and currents which have
previously been spoken of. His lantern swung from his tightly clenched hand.
Though the body was erect, the head was thrown back so that the closed eyes were
pointed towards the needle of the telltale that swung from a beam in the ceiling.
Footnote. The cabin compass is called the telltale because without going to
the compass at the helm, the captain, while below, can inform himself of the
course of the ship. End of footnote.
Terrible old man, thought Starbucks with a shudder. Sleeping in this gale, still
thou steadfastly eyes thy purpose.